Meier mss., 1927-2010
Indiana University Digital Library Program
- Writings and speeches, 1955-2009, undated (Box 5)
  - Speeches, 1980-2008, undated (Box 8)
    - Dated Speeches, 1980-2008
      - Thomas-Debs Address, 1988, May 7, Notecards, notes
        Includes program
      - Bank St. College Graduation Speech, 1988, May, 2 drafts
      - Speech notes, 1989, May 9
      - Turning Points Conference speech, 1989, June 16, 2 drafts
      - Speech notes, ca. 1990, Apr. 25
      - Michigan speech, 1990, May 20
      - Becoming a Teacher, 16th annual DeGarmo Lecture, 1991, Apr. 4, undated, 3 drafts, 4 programs
      - NPR, 1991, Dec. 22-24
      - CPESS speech, 1992, Jan. 12
      - Marianne Amarel Memorial Lecture Series, 1992, Apr. 3, undated, Transcript, notes
        Includes 11 cards with audience comments
      - Second Biennial Marianne Amarel Memorial Lecture: Changing Our Habits of Schooling, 1993, Jan. 23-30, undated, 2 drafts, 2 transcripts
      - Creating a National Elementary Schools Network, 1993, Apr. 25
      - Retreat speech, 1993, Apr. 29-30, 4 drafts
        Includes CPESS Staff Development Day schedule
      - Why Kids Don't Want to be Well-Educated, 1993-1994
        See also: Speech to ASCD in Alexandria
        - Speech, 1993, Apr., 7 drafts
        - Requests for copies of the speech, 1993, Jan. 22-Apr. 1994, undated
      - Small Schools Speech in Philadelphia, 1993, May 6-Aug. 27, undated, 6 drafts
        Includes a note from Deborah Meier and a request for a copy of the speech
      - Can We Impose a Democratic Education on Kids? Speech in Israel, 1993, June, 2 drafts
        See also: International Conference of Education for Democracy in a Multicultural Society in Jerusalem, Israel
      - Women's American ORT convention speech, 1993, Oct. 15-Nov. 2, 1 draft
        Includes program, letter from Women's American ORT, and article Women's ORT Convenes Here on convention
        See also: Women's American ORT / Miami Beach VHS; Oversize 3, folder 16 (article Women's ORT Convenes Here)
      - Speech to ASCD in Alexandria (Revised from Why Kids Don't Want to be Well-Educated), 1993, Oct., 5 drafts
        See also: Why Kids Don't Want to be Well-Educated
      - Speech to CES in SF, 1994, Mar. 24, 2 drafts
      - Why Educate? The 1994 Martin Buskin Memorial Lecture, 1994, Apr. 16
        See: Writings removed from binder pocket, 1 printed
      - Graduation speech, 1994, June
      - Speech at Ford Foundation on Annenberg Foundation grant, 1994, Sept. 21, undated, 2 drafts
        See also: City Bar 12/1 speech
      - Speech on Annenberg grant, 1994, Dec., 4 drafts
      - Speech, 1995, Jan. 11
      - Caswell speech: Does It Matter? 1995, Mar.
      - Speech, 1995, July
      - Speech, 1995, Sept. 21
      - Keynote address, New York University Review of Law & Social Change, 1994-1995, 1 draft, 2 printed
      - Israel speech, 1995, 2 drafts
      - Draft outline for remarks, 1996, Jan. 28
      - Illinois speech, 1996, Mar. 8
      - If Schools Were Authentic, 1996, Mar.-Apr. 8, 3 drafts
      - Smallness for ASCD, 1996, Apr. 9
      - Democracy notes, 1996, Apr. 9
      - Hirsch Colloquium on Jewish Schooling and the Jewish Future, 1996, May 5, 3 drafts
      - Speech notes, 1996, Nov.
      - Pittsburgh speech, 1996, Dec. 3, 2 drafts
      - The Power of Our Ideas: What Will It Take to Remake Schools. UIC Small School Workshop, 1996, Dec. 13
        Includes letter from University of Illinois at Chicago
      - Why, 1997, Jan. 4
      - Accountability: The View from the School, Panasonic Foundation Conference, 1997, Mar. 1-3
      - Schooling and The Crisis of Relationships, CES National Congress, 1997, Nov. 6, 2 drafts
      - Lesley College commencement speech, 1998, May 27, 3 drafts
        See also: Lesley College commencement programs
      - Salisbury speech, 1998, Oct.
      - Coalition Fall Forum, 1998, Nov.-1999, Jan. 26, 2 drafts (Box 9)
      - Testimony re: Pilot Schools, 1998, Dec. 9, 2 drafts
      - Our Challenge: To Set the Highest Possible Standards for Human Relationships. Rural Annenberg Challenge, 1998, Sept. 30-1999, Feb. 9, 2 drafts
        Includes correspondence and symposium brochure
      - Speech in SF, 1999, Mar. 7, 3 drafts
      - Speech notes, ca. 2001, Nov. 22, 3 drafts
      - Speech notes, 2003, Jan. 29
      - Democracy/Trust, 2003, Jan. 31
      - Hudson, 2003, Apr. 5, 2 drafts
      - Brookings Institution speech, 2003, May 2-2004, Aug. 18, 5 drafts
      - Getting the Governance Thing Right, 2003, Nov.
      - Resistance and Courage, and What it is to be a Teacher These Days, 2004, Apr. 13-July 9, undated, 4 drafts
      - Speech in honor of Ted Sizer, 2005, Nov. 3
      - NCLB [No Child Left Behind], 2006, Apr. 24, 2 drafts
      - Jewish education, 2006, June 20
      - Quick Fixes and more, 2006, Dec.
      - Speech at panel on Shanker, 2007, 2 drafts
      - Release of Democracy at Risk by the Forum for Education and Democracy. National Press Club, Washington D.C., 2008, Apr. 23
      - With Diane Ravitch. Great Debate: Resolved: A Stronger Federal Role in Education is Needed in the 21st Century. Lessons from NCLB and Beyond, 2008, Sept. 24
        Includes correspondence, participant packet
    - Undated Speeches, undated
      Arranged alphabetically by speech title
      - Achievement Gap, undated, 2 drafts
      - Are Small Schools the Way to Go? undated
      - ASPEN Speech, undated
      - CES Speech, undated, 2 drafts
      - City Bar 12/1 speech, undated, 2 drafts
        See also: Speech at Ford Foundation on Annenberg Foundation grant
      - Community: Keeping School, 8/19, undated
      - Compassionate Conservatism, undated
      - Democracy and Testing, undated, 2 drafts
      - Driving Honesty Out of Education, undated
      - DSA Our Dreams speech, undated, 2 drafts
      - Love and Hate, undated
      - Opening Remarks [MCAS], undated
      - Presentation at Albany Conference, undated, 5 drafts
      - Response to Dr. Honig, undated, 5 drafts
        Includes 1988 History-Social Science Framework booklet and notecard
      - Progressivism and Secondary Ed, undated, Notecards, 2 drafts
      - Standards, undated, 2 drafts
    - Hearings, Testimonies, and Affidavits, 1973-2003, undated
      - Why Johnny Can't Read: testimony before a hearing at Hunter College, 1973, Apr. 6, 2 transcripts
      - Minimum Competency Testing Clarification Hearing, 1981, July 8
      - Congressional Hearing on Youth and Violence, 1989
        - Correspondence and related documents, 1989
        - 8 drafts and 1 transcript of testimony, 1989
          Includes correspondence with Ruth Jordan of Hager, Sharp and Abramson
        - Articles on hearing and Central Park attack, 1989
      - Statement to Massachusetts State Board of Education, 1997, Feb. 10
      - Testimony to Mass. School Board Regarding Uses/Misuses of Standardized Testing and the Current MCAS Tests, 1999, Sept. 27
      - Affidavit, Commonwealth of Massachusetts, 2003, Mar. 20, 2 transcripts
      - Testimony for NY State House and Senate Education Committees, 2003, Oct. 22, 2 drafts
      - NY State Hearing, 2008, Sept. 18
      - Testimony, undated, 2 drafts
      - Testimony of Deborah W. Meier re Testing Practices: Do They Help or Hurt Our Children? Undated, 2 drafts
        Includes Reading Tests: Do they help or hurt your child? booklet
    - Memorial Remarks, 1989-2007, undated
      Arranged alphabetically by the name of the subject
      - Harrington, Michael, 1989, 2 drafts
        Includes memorial program and flyer, memorial speech by Roberta Lynch
      - Mendelson, Saul, 1998
        Includes memorial service program and packet of testimonials
      - Russell, Myra, undated, 2 drafts
      - Shier, Carl Marx, 2007
        2 drafts, notes, 3 memorial service programs
  - Drafts and notes for articles and speeches, 1955-2008, undated (Box 9)
    - As I think back to the early days with Room 104 I realize that my affection for these children was slow in coming..., undated (Folder 1)
      Includes correspondence and excerpt from Anti-Intellectualism in America by Richard Hoffstadter
    - Wishful Thinking--Intro, 1st draft for book on playgrounds, Is the idea of democracy truly just wishful thinking? undated (Folder 2)
    - Democracy and Schooling Connections, Assumption re equal worth..., undated
    - Theobald--essay, 10/29, When I was born, the majority of Americans didn't start high school, much less drop out of it..., undated, 2 drafts (Folder 3)
    - Let me count the ways: (1) garbage in, garbage out..., undated
    - 43 years in various roles as a public school parent, teacher and principal has taught me that having the 'power to' coerce is not the answer..., undated
    - There's something wrong with the education debate in this nation. It doesn't ring true. It's off key somehow..., 1993, Aug., 3 drafts (Folder 4)
    - Newsday piece, Never in the history of the world has any nation succeeded in educating all its children well..., 1996, Sept. 2 (Folder 5)
    - For the past year I had dealt in my community with increasingly militant parent organizations and accepted as typical the crescendo of local anti-school..., 1968 (Folder 6)
    - Massive government sponsored statistical studies, such as the Office of Education's Equality of Educational Opportunity, rarely are expected to turn up anything new or suggest startling innovations..., ca. 1966
    - The new middle class (professionals, bureaucrats, managers, etc.), notes sociologist ca. Wright Mills in his now famous WHITE COLLAR, are..., ca. 1955
    - Re teacher as conservative: Thought. Part of the task of change will involve finding new metaphors..., 1989, Aug. 2
    - Education/Conversation, A good intellectual education is an invitation to join a conversation..., undated
    - Debbie article, In part it is merely accidental that schools are the target area of the urban crisis today, rather than employment or housing..., undated
    - Outline. Introduction. I. The School Vs. Parents Today. Gone are the old fighting slogans--bussing, neighborhood schools, integration--that only yesterday, it seems, stirred parents..., undated
    - If you don't care where you're going then any road will get you there..., undated
    - Raywid draft, Small schools were once the norm..., 2004, Nov. 27, 2 drafts
      Includes correspondence from Mary Anne Raywid
    - Accountability: what's the 'right' model?/The End Justifies the Means? 4/18, Thoughts for a piece on accountability/our current society seems to have confused accountability for responsibility..., undated
    - The End Justifies the Means? Our current society seems to have confused accountability for responsibility..., 2002, June 4
      Includes newspaper clipping
    - Empathy, Empathy is a tricky business..., 1994, Dec. 16 (Folder 7)
    - Re: Request for Action. From: Deborah Meier, The idea is right and very necessary. Thank you for trying to do this much needed task..., 1998, June 17
    - Brown v. Board of Education Anniversary, It was the beginning of what might have been a critical turning point..., 2004, Apr. 21
      Includes correspondence from Lauren Hillman
    - Tests, Driver's test analogy... 'Don't tell me, show me' is an idea that's hardly new. And schooling was once all about that spirit..., undated
    - There are many different answers, depending on what the question is..., undated, 2 drafts
    - Topic: What does it mean for today's secondary school graduates to be educated? There are times these days when it's hard to remember that schools actually are intended for a social purpose...
    - 780 words on school governance, The nation's genius has been in its constant struggle to maintain an appropriate balance of power in the interests of justice on one hand and liberty on the other..., undated
    - 650 words on school governance, When I was born most Americans did not start high school; today we are committed to seeing that every child completes high school with the strengths to use his or her mind well on behalf of his or her own future and the nation's..., undated, 2 drafts
    - [Thomas Jefferson quote] The question of how best to 'inform their discretion' while retaining control by 'the people' is the task facing democratic-minded school reformers..., undated
    - Purposes, The language we commonly use in everyday conversation, newspaper editorials and political speeches to explain the value of a K-12 education (or for that matter a college education) has important repercussions..., undated
    - [Lillian Katz quote] Lillian Katz' statement is my mantra as a philosophy of political life: but it's absurd to imagine that schools are able to achieve this..., undated
    - Public Engagement, 1. Do we mean it when we say it..., undated
    - Imaginative Play, Family--adult roles in society..., 2008, Jan. 30
    - The Cost of a Good Education, Tuition at NYC's 'better' private schools..., undated
    - Effective Schools, I want to explore--map the terrain, the issues that have placed me so squarely 'against' the phenomenon of MES..., undated (Folder 8)
      Includes article by Eleanor Duckworth ...what teachers know: the best knowledge base...
    - More tries, 1/27, What gaps can we close? What gaps are there by definition?..., undated (Folder 9)
    - So what are you doing to close the achievement gap, a Foundation officer challenged me after visiting MH..., 2000, Oct.
    - Choice: Changing Schools, There are a lot of reasons to be for choice... 1991, Dec. (Folder 10)
    - Essay on School Reform with Sandra Feldman, Teacher unionists and school reformers seem unlikely partners..., 1995
    - 3rd Nation piece, The idea that nearly all our fellow citizens have something approximating equal intelligence..., 1996
    - At Central Park East Elementary School we accept responsibility--'accountability'--for our student's school programs..., undated
    - What the central purpose of the public's incarceration of its youth for 8-10-12-now 14 years..., 2006, Notecards (Folder 11)
    - Various notes for multiple speeches, 1988, undated (Folder 12)
    - SQR (School Quality Review), There is no greater danger facing us than surrounding our youth with powerless adults and powerless communities..., undated (Folder 13)
    - All reform is not an advance. All change is not good..., undated
    - On trust, predictability and not knowing..., undated
    - Thoughts on race and class, Race and class--without any doubt effect test scores..., undated
    - Draft ideas, The Networks for School Renewal grows naturally out of both the national reform agenda and the reform work taking place in New York City over the past decade...
    - Being in Philadelphia: 1960s--More recent experiences..., undated
    - Of course, it's very hard to be sure if one's own mood is strictly personal, or corresponds to some larger societal phenomenon..., undated (Folder 14)
    - Working class doesn't accept its historic mission!..., undated
    - Anyone operating in the arena of politics is always making estimates of reality on a scale beyond their own personal, eye-witness perception..., undated
    - Draft fragment, p.2-8, undated
    - Being a radical, liberal, left-winger or socialist doesn't solve all problems of parenthood!..., undated
    - 1 page of notes, undated
    - Grade 5, Form F, Student Booklet (Test packet), 1983
    - Effective Schools (notebook), undated (Folder 15)
    - [Speech on Ted Sizer], I almost missed this evening!..., undated, 2 drafts (Folder 16)
    - [Speech on Vito Perrone], Vito and I taught a course together several times..., undated, 3 drafts (Folder 17)
    - Bio, what's at stake, we're debating what matters..., undated, 2 drafts (Folder 18)
    - I. Introduction. I came prepared for a debate, and so I'm a bit rattled by having Dr. Coffman steal my thunder..., undated (Folder 19)
    - I think, over the years, I've begun a million speeches with 'it's both the best and worst of all times'..., undated (Folder 20)
    - The notion, the wildly optimistic idea, that human beings are capable of consciously organizing and influencing..., undated (Folder 21)
    - Time mag, Neither candidate has yet faced up to the crisis..., 1988, Aug. 17
    - The NY City school system's propensity to publish irrelevant data about important educational matters such as students' reading performance..., undated
    - It's a puzzling moment..., It's a puzzling moment. At one and the same time we're telling kids that getting a good education..., undated (Folder 22)
    - Buzz words of today are interesting..., undated (Box 10, Folder 23)
    - Ideas and opinions, Cross road--exciting and depressing..., undated
    - Speech outline, I. CPESS experience--early pioneers in use of standards vs. credit hours..., undated
    - We could spend our time trading statistics--and each insisting the other's data is wrong..., undated
    - Speech, Alice-in-Wonderland quality of much of the education debate. I wrote In Schools We Trust to try to make a case for a different way of seeing..., undated
    - Nervous, stage fright, public speaking, etc. Shoes. My fascination with public schools overlapped with my early years of parenting, my activity in the civil rights movement..., undated
    - Draft fragment, p. 14-17, The weekly Newsletters that went home were a part of this effort to make our work transparent..., undated
    - Draft fragment, p. 3-43, Friends told me at the time, in defense of their spreading the lies or allowing them to be spread..., undated
    - FF '02?, Themes! Hope and optimism--but as you'll see... well it was hard not to get side-tracked..., ca. 2002 (Folder 24)
    - New teacher/old teacher, 40 yrs ago, Thirty years ago..., undated
    - Draft fragment, p. 3-14, But why is it so one-sided? E.g. our school ranking looks pretty good! Why isn't this reported?..., undated
    - Patriotism issue quotes. Ravitch stuff: But to deprive students of an education that allows them to see themselves as part of this land..., undated
    - It ought to be a moment in history to rejoice. A conservative federal government has expressed its certainty that ALL children..., undated
    - Is teaching to improve test scores a good educ! Freire and Dewey, similarities and differences..., undated
    - Since I was born--nearly 70 years ago--we've proclaimed a startling new idea..., ca. 1999-2001
    - Who We Are Now, by Sam Roberts. Not adjusted for inflation--wages have doubled since 1981..., undated
    - Draft fragment, p. 20-25, Describe: We decided that a school needed to be small enough so that all the adults who had to be together to make school-wide decisions could fit easily into one room..., undated
    - Draft 1, Sunday, May 31, We must keep kids in school for at least 13 long years--at public expense--for some good reason..., undated (Folder 25)
    - CPESS and Democracy, If the primary public responsibility and justification for tax-supported schooling is raising a generation of fellow citizens..., undated
    - Clinchy: Supposing that. In trying to imagine what schools might be like if we weren't thinking about what colleges want..., undated (Folder 26)
    - We've been claiming for 20-30 years that we need better educ citizenry and workforce..., undated
    - I've had a wonderful 30 year adventure..., undated
    - KGTN Private, All kids--It's doable, CPE, It's harder than we think..., undated
    - Best and worst 25 yrs..., undated
    - Buy the book--so I don't have to retell it today!..., undated (Folder 27)
    - School lasts 6 hours a day--1 out of 4. School operates 180 days--1 out of every 2..., undated
    - Special education, My book; vs. the topic of this lecture; trust and company with adults..., undated
    - The emperor wears no clothes--NCLB is a sham--It's got the problem wrong as well as the solution..., undated
    - Minn. standards, All Kids are Alternative, Fortunately, unfortunately, best and worst of all time?..., undated (Folder 28)
    - Speech notes, Buy 1000 copies of my book. Study that women self-assess less..., undated (Folder 29)
    - What's it All About, The reformers--from whom I increasingly distance myself--seem agreed..., undated
    - Introduction: Whose my audience? What can I assume? Especially with so many family and old friends..., undated
    - Articles to be, miscellaneous drafts and related article, 1980, undated (Folder 30)
    - Articles to be, miscellaneous drafts and related article, 1980, undated (Box 3)
    - Draft fragment, p. 2, It might seem reasonable (however misleading) that those who originally sought to design IQ tests..., undated (Box 10, Folder 31)
    - Draft fragment, p. 2, ...and futility--because that is a message that emboldens out enemies..., undated
    - The opening gambit of many social conversations these days begins well, what do you think about merit pay?..., undated
    - In addressing this question three quite disparate circumstances come to my mind..., undated
    - Possible alternative way of starting, Each step along the way occurred rather by accident, although in retrospect there seeemed to be a plan..., undated
    - Rewrite!, It's hard not to be happy at being center-stage again, and finding others interested in what you know most about..., undated
    - A. At least 5 characteristics of a good school..., undated (Folder 32)
    - 10 yrs ago--part of never-ending upward spiral..., undated, Notecards (Folder 33)
    - Connection between socialism and feminism..., undated, Notecards (Folder 34)
    - Miscellaneous draft fragments, undated
    - p 2, 1) creation springs only from..., undated, Notebook (Folder 35)
    - Miscellaneous draft fragments, undated
    - Only 10 years or so ago we assumed we were a part of a never-ending upward spiral..., 1975-1976
    - People ask me... is open ed an experiment? If so--in contrast to what?..., undated
    - Rdg Tests, 1. History--what are they supposed to measure?..., undated
    - Miscellaneous draft fragments on reading tests, undated
    - I was out on a bike jaunt Sunday afternoon and ran into an old acquaintance--a deputy supt in another NYC school district..., undated, 2 drafts
    - Symbol/substance..., undated
    - Spring 1974--an accident..., undated, Notecards (Folder 36)
    - Like children who have invested their faith in the fallible adult..., undated, Notecards
    - A long time since... gave it up... Assessment (sometimes called testing) and its attendant, accountability..., undated (Folder 37)
    - What everyone should know makes for a fun parlor game..., undated
    - CPESS and District 4, At the heart of what we mean by a good school is one whose central priority is the development of the intellectual, social, and ethical habits..., undated
    - Tchg/Learning requires people to not only learn new ideas/skills/knowledge but unlearn--change--alter--reorganize..., undated
    - (1) A punishment, in our vocabulary, we decided was an action we took..., undated
    - The question then is..., undated, Notecards (Folder 38)
    - Latest Ed Wk pieces on values..., undated, Notecards
    - Miscellaneous notes, undated, Notecards (Folder 39)
    - I. Contradictions, hope and despair, some facts..., undated, Notecards
    - Or as another example--think of the mild reaction of most of us to the million horrors of our day..., undated, Notecards
    - Are schools worse than ever? Are schools turning out more illiterates than in the past?..., undated (Folder 40)
    - Outline, Rationale: We're in one of those periods of particularly fierce criticism of public education..., undated
    - In the name of a return to basics we are witnessing a massive forgetting of what it was about the nostalgized traditions of the past that might be worth valuing..., undated, 2 drafts